Alan Freed Collection ARC.0006
Library and Archives
Alan Freed Collection
Bulk, 1954-1965
1921-1999, undated
ARC.0006
Library and Archives
16.01 Linear feet (1 records carton, 1 Hollinger box, 3 half Hollinger boxes, 1 shared flat file drawer, tube)
The Alan Freed Collection spans the years 1918 to 1992, with the bulk of the collection dating between 1954 and 1964. The collection consists primarily of financial and court documents relating to the commercial bribery case brought by the City of New York against Alan Freed, known as "Payola." These files contain accounting records, Assistant District Attorney notes, cancelled checks, contracts, correspondence, indictments, invoices, memoranda, music clearance sheets, reports, State of New York Grand Jury exhibits, subpoenas, witness statements and summaries, as well as many duplicate and annotated photocopies of documents. Other materials in the collection relate to Freed’s renowned career as a radio, television, and film personality and include lobby cards, magazine articles, movie posters, programs, an audio and video recording, sheet music, and yearbooks. The collection as a whole illustrates Freed's impact on the early history of rock and roll. Seen in a broader context, the collection provides insights to the recording and broadcasting industries in the 1950s and early 1960s, the resulting “Payola” scandal, and its long-lasting effects.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights statement on the Researcher Registration form before using this collection. Series VII: 2011 Accruals is CLOSED until a signed gift agreement can be secured from the donor. Some of the materials in the collection are confidential and, therefore, are RESTRICTED. Redacted access copies of the confidential documents are available in the collection. The condition of some of the audiovisual materials in the collection has not yet been determined for playback purposes. Some of the audiovisual materials in the collection are on defunct media formats and, therefore, are RESTRICTED. Access copies of these materials may have to be created prior to use. Consult the Library and Archives staff in advance of your visit to ensure access to these materials is available.
Custodial History note
The Alan Freed Collection was received by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame Foundation, Inc. as a permanent loan from Judith Fisher Freed on August 29, 2002. An accrual to the Alan Freed Collection was received by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Inc. as a restricted gift from Judith Fisher Freed on August 30, 2011.
Biographical Note
1921 December 15 Albert James Freed is born in Johnston, Pa.
1933 The Freed family moves to Salem, Ohio.
1942 Freed is hired for his first broadcasting job by WKST in New Castle, Pa., as host of a nightly classical music program.
1943 Hired as a sportscaster at WKBN in Youngstown, Ohio.
1945 Hired as a disc jockey at WAKR-AM in Akron, Ohio, playing hot jazz and pop recordings.
1949 Hired at WXEL-TV in Cleveland, Ohio and hosts the afternoon movie.
1951 July 11 Leo Mintz convinces him to emcee a rhythm and blues program on WJW-AM in Cleveland.
1952 March 25 Organized with Mintz and Lew Platt, the Moondog Coronation Ball is held at the Cleveland Arena and is considered the country’s first rock and roll concert.
1954 September Hired as a disc jockey by WINS in New York, N.Y.
1955 Promotes the first of many live shows in New York City.
1956 Stars in Rock Around The Rock as himself, the first of five film appearances.
1957 Hired by ABC-TV to emcee a rock and roll dance show Alan Freed’s Big Beat; show is canceled months later after controversy over performer Frankie Lymon dancing with a white teenager.
1958 May Arrested and charged with inciting a riot at a Boston, Massachusetts concert he promoted; the charges are dropped. Fired by WINS. Hired by WABC in New York, N.Y.
1959 Fired by WABC.
1960 February 26 Indicted for commercial bribery in the state of New York.
1960 Hired as a disc jockey by KDAY in Los Angeles, California.
1962 Pleads guilty to two charges of commercial bribery.
1965 January 20 Dies of complications from alcoholism in Palm Springs, Ca.
1986 January 23 Inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.
1988 Inducted into the Radio Hall of Fame.
2002 Ashes are interred at the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum in Cleveland.
Alan Freed, the disc jockey who became famous for coining the term “rock and roll” to describe the rhythm and blues records he was broadcasting, began what would become a revolutionary radio career in New Castle, Pennsylvania in 1942. By 1951 Freed was in Cleveland, Ohio and working in television. Record Rendezvous owner Leo Mintz urged Freed to host a radio program featuring African-American rhythm and blues, based on the increasing number of white teenagers buying “race records” at his store. On July 11, 1951 Freed began hosting what he called the "Moondog's Rock 'n' Roll Party," with Freed himself as the "Moondog." The popularity of the program quickly grew and, by March of 1952, Freed was promoting his own Moondog Coronation Ball concert, recognized by many as the first rock and roll concert ever held. The concert was oversold and between 15,000-20,000 teenagers attempted to fill the Cleveland venue with a seating capacity of only 12,500. The concert was quickly shutdown, and Freed’s notoriety grew, leading to a job offer from WINS in New York, which was changing its programming format to rock and roll.
Once in New York, Freed’s popularity and influence continued to grow. He engaged in the common practice of accepting payments or writing credits to get air time for certain records (as Freed did for Chuck Berry’s “Maybellene”). This would become known as “payola” and was Freed’s ultimate downfall. But, at WINS from 1954-1958, Freed enjoyed a success that few disc jockeys ever achieved. He promoted live shows, was interviewed in print and on television, starred in films, and hosted a television dance show and his own radio show. Then in 1959 he was fired by WABC for refusing to sign a “practices in the selection of music for broadcast affidavit,” stating that he never accepted incentives for playing records. In early 1960, he was indicted on 26 counts of commercial bribery in the State of New York. He would ultimately plead guilty to two counts, receive a suspended sentence, and pay a $300 fine.
Freed never again enjoyed the success or influence he had in the 1950s, moving from radio station to radio station in California and Florida, and eventually died of kidney and liver failure from alcoholism. Regardless, his reputation as a pioneer in the history of radio, and rock and roll in particular, remains intact. He was inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame as part of its inaugural class in 1986 and into the Radio Hall of Fame in 1988. Finally in 2002, as part of an exhibit dedicated to the “Architects of Rock and Roll,” Alan Freed’s ashes were interred at the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum in Cleveland, Ohio.
Sources
"Alan Freed Biography." Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum. Accessed June 1, 2010. http://rockhall.com/inductees/alan-freed/bio/.
Fong-Torres, Ben. “Alan Freed Biography.” Accessed June 1, 2010. http://www.alanfreed.com/biography.html
“Freed, Alan.” eNotes. Accessed June 21, 2010. http://www.enotes.com/contemporary-musicians/freed-alan-biography.
Recommended Resources
Freed, Judith Fisher. Alan Freed. Accessed October 10, 2011. http://www.alanfreed.com.
Jackson, John A. Big Beat Heat: Alan Freed and the Early Years of Rock & Roll. New York: Schirmer Books, 1991.
Accruals note
Accruals to the collection are located in Series VII.
Separated Materials
Commercial recordings and publications have been transferred to the library collection. Please search for the "Alan Freed Collection" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles.
Related Archival Materials
Related materials providing content on Alan Freed may be found in the following collections in this repository: Terry Stewart Collection. Related materials may also be found in other collections that constitute a part of the Northeast Ohio Popular Music Archives.
Berry, Chuck; Clanton, Jimmy; Clark, Dick, 1929-; Freed, Alan; Freed, Judith Fisher; Haley, Bill, 1925-1981; Northeast Ohio Popular Music Archives; Correspondence; Disc jockeys; Film posters; Music trade--United States.; Periodicals; Radio personalities; Rock concerts; Rock music--To 1961.; Rock music--United States.; Sound recording industry--United States--Corrupt practices.
- Series I: Financial Records [RESTRICTED], 1943-1967, undated
  Access Restrictions
  Some of the materials in this series are confidential and, therefore, are RESTRICTED. Redacted access copies of the confidential documents are available in the collection.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I: Financial Records [RESTRICTED] contains documents pertaining to the employment and business dealings of Alan Freed, including accounting records, cancelled checks, contracts, correspondence, invoices, music clearance sheets, and photographs. Some of the documents in this section were also used as State of New York Grand Jury exhibits for the People v. Freed court case. Files are arranged alphabetically by company and by individual.
  - Subseries 1: Action Records, 1959
    Scope and Contents
    Subseries I: Action Records contains one file of cancelled checks. Checks are arranged chronologically.
    - Cancelled checks
      - #1615, #1616, #1617 – Check Register, 1959 September 2-1959 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 1, Object 1)
      - #1615 – Louis Klayman, 1959 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 1, Object 2)
      - #1756, #1757, #1758 – Check Register, 1959 October 2-1959 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 1, Object 3)
      - #1757 - Louis Klayman, 1959 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 1, Object 4)
      - #1936, #1937, #1938 – Check Register, 1959 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 1, Object 5)
      - #1937 – Louis Klayman, 1959 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 1, Object 6)
  - Subseries 2: Alpha Distributing Company (ADC), 1956-1957, undated
    Subseries II: ADC contains one file of cancelled checks. Checks are arranged chronologically with District Attorney's information for the Payola case located at the end.
    - Cancelled checks
      - #6711 – Alan Freed, 1956 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 2, Object 1)
      - #7196 – Gotham Broadcasting Corporation, 1956 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 2, Object 2)
      - #7630 – Gotham Broadcasting Corporation, 1957 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 2, Object 3-4)
      - District Attorney’s Office envelope with Alpha checks for payment of Alan Freed's Live [Budget], undated (Box 1, Folder 2, Object 5)
  - Subseries 3: American Broadcasting Company (ABC), 1958-1959, undated
    Subseries III: ABC includes files related to accounting, advertising, contracts with local facilities, correspondence, and music clearance sheets from the Alan Freed Show. Files are in alphabetical order by title. Items in the files are arranged chronologically. Some of the items in this subseries are photocopies of original documents; some are annotated.
    - Accounting, 1958-1959, undated
      - Freed, Alan earnings, 1958 June 2-1959 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 1)
      - Detail of total earnings paid to Alan Freed, 1958 June 2-1959 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 2)
      - Freed, Alan - Barracuda Music and Bonaire Music, Inc., page 5, 1958 August 28-1959 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 3)
      - Freed, Alan substitutes, 1958 August 29-1959 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 4)
      - Invoice #12-7038 to Barracuda Music, Inc., 1958 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 5)
      - Freed, Alan analysis - account #112-3, 1958 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 6)
      - Freed, Alan accounting, 1958 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 7)
      - Accounting ledger, 1958 November 1-1959 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 8)
      - Invoice #12-7185 to Barracuda Music, Inc., 1958 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 9)
      - Invoice #12-7373 to Barracuda Music, Inc., 1959 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 10)
      - Invoice #12-1276 to Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 11)
      - Invoice #12-7482 to Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 12)
      - Invoice #12-1390 to Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 13)
      - Authorization for payment to artists and billing to client payee, Alan Freed, 1959 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 14)
      - AFTRA pension and welfare funds, 1959 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 15-16)
      - Invoice #12-1771 to Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 17)
      - Invoice #12-7758 to Mr. Alan Freed/Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 18)
      - Invoice #12-1859 to Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 19)
      - Invoice #12-7850 to Mr. Alan Freed/Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 20)
      - Invoice #12-7851 to Mr. Alan Freed, 1959 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 21)
      - Summary of payments, 1959 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 22)
      - The Alan Freed Show participation, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 23)
      - Accounts receivable Alan Freed, account #112-3, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Object 24)
    - Advertising, 1957-1958
      - Rate Card #19, 1958 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 4, Object 1)
    - Contracts – local facilities, 1958 September-1959 August
      - 1958 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 5, Object 1)
      - 1958 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 5, Object 2-3)
      - 1959 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 5, Object 4-5)
      - 1959 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 5, Object 6-7)
    - Correspondence, 1958 May-1959 November
      - To Alan Freed - employment contract, 1958 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 1-2)
      - Unilateral changes by ABC in Alan Freed Show, 1958 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 3)
      - Interdepartmental correspondence - subject: Barracuda Music, Inc. 1958 August 27-1958 September 6, 1958 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 4)
      - Interdepartmental correspondence - subject: Alan Freed substitutes, 1958 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 5)
      - Interdepartmental correspondence - subject: The Alan Freed Show, 1959 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 6)
      - Interdepartmental correspondence - subject: Alan Freed, 1959 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 7)
        General note
        Letter of termination attached.
      - Interdepartmental correspondence - subject: Barracuda Music, Inc. 1958 October 6-1959 January 3, 1959 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 8)
      - To Alan Freed - employment contract, 1959 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 9-11)
      - Interdepartment correspondence - subject Bonaire Music, Inc. 1959 March 2-1959 April 4, 1959 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 12)
      - To Alan Freed - employment contract, 1959 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 13-15)
      - From Ben Hoberman to Jack Hooke, 1959 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 16)
      - Interdepartmental correspondence - subject: Bonaire Music, Inc. 1959 August 12-1959 September 12, 1959 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 17-18)
      - Practices in the selection of music for broadcast affidavit, 1959 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 19-21)
      - From Alan Freed to American Broadcasting Company - re: practices in the selection of music for broadcast affidavit, 1959 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 22-24)
        Museum Accession Number
        Object 22 (original): A2010.1.10
        Separated Materials
        Original document on exhibit. Consult the Library and Archives staff in advance of your visit for additional information.
      - To Alan Freed - termination of contract, 1959 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 25)
      - Interdepartmental correspondence - subject: Alan Freed, 1962 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 26)
      - From State of New York Department of Labor Division of Employment to American Broadcasting Paramount Theatres, Inc., 1962 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 6, Object 27)
    - Music clearance sheets for the Alan Freed Show, 1959 November
      - 1959 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 1)
      - 1959 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 2)
      - 1959 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 3)
      - 1959 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 4)
      - 1959 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 5)
      - 1959 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 6)
      - 1959 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 7)
      - 1959 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 8)
      - 1959 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 9)
      - 1959 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 10)
      - 1959 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 11)
        Pages 1-3 on exhibit. Consult the Library and Archives staff in advance of your visit for additional information.
        A2010.1.9
      - 1959 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 12)
      - 1959 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 13)
      - 1959 November (Box 1, Folder 7, Object 14)
  - Subseries 4: American Guild of Variety Artists, 1961
    - American Guild of Variety Artists, 1961 November 17
      - Receipt #14958 to Alan Freed for $202 "toward claims" (Box 1, Folder 8, Object 1)
  - Subseries 5: Barracuda Music, Inc., 1958-1959
    Subseries V: Barracuda Music contains accounting documents and contracts. Files are arranged alphabetically. Items within the files are organized chronologically.
    - Accounting, 1958-1959
      - Announcements given by Alan Freed, 1958 August 28-1958 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 9, Object 1)
      - Statement of income and expenses, 1959 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 9, Object 2)
        2 photocopies
    - Contract, circa 1958
      - Agreement between Barracuda Music, Inc. and Firm Amusement Corporation (Box 1, Folder 10, Object 1)
  - Subseries 6: Bonaire Music, Inc., 1959-1960
    Subseries VI: contains Bonaire Music accounting records. Items are organized chronologically. Some items are annotated.
    - Accounting, 1959 March-1960 January
      - Announcements given by Alan Freed, 1959 March 2-1959 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 1)
      - Ledger - Bonaire Music, Inc. at Brooklyn Fox Theatre, 1959 March 27-1959 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 2-3)
      - Ledger - Bonaire Music, Inc. at Brooklyn Fox Theatre and State Theater, 1959 April 7, 1959 September 15, 1959 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 4-5)
      - Announcements given by Alan Freed, 1959 August 12-1959 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 6)
      - Bonaire Music, Inc. at Brooklyn Fox Theatre, 1959 September 4-1959 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 7-8)
      - Bonaire Music, Inc. / Trade Bank & Trust Company, 1959 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 9)
      - Bonaire Music, Inc. at State Theater-Hartford, 1959 September 19-1959 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 10-11)
      - Bonaire Music, Inc., 1960 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 11, Object 12)
  - Subseries 7: John Brantley, 1958-1960
    Subseries VII: John Brantley contains checks made payable to Brantley, who worked as Alan Freed's assistant from September 7, 1954 to November 1959. The checks are written from a number of different companies, including Alpha Distributing Company, Stamford Productions, Superior Record Sales, and W.S.F. Checks are arranged chronologically.
    - Checks made payable to, 1958 April-1960 February
      - Superior Record Sales Company Inc. – #1330, 1958 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 1)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #10307, 1958 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 2)
      - Stamford Productions – #187, 1958 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 3)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #1402, 1958 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 4)
      - Stamford Productions – #234, 1958 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 5)
      - Superior Record Sales Company Incorporated – #2172, 1958 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 6)
      - Superior Record Sales Company Incorporated – #2195, 1958 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 7)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #2065, 1958 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 8)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #2245, 1959 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 9)
      - Superior Record Sales Company Incorporated – #2476, 1959 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 10)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #2675, 1959 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 11)
      - W.S.F., Incorporated – #172, 1959 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 12)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #3302, 1959 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 13)
      - Superior Record Sales Company Incorporated – #2871, 1959 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 14)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #3786, 1959 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 15)
      - Superior Record Sales Company Incorporated – #3381, 1959 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 16)
      - Alpha Distributing Company – #4039, 1959 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 17)
      - District Attorney’s Office envelope with John Brantley's cancelled checks, 1960 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 18)
      - District Attorney’s Office envelope with John Brantley's cancelled checks, 1960 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 12, Object 19)
  - Subseries 8: Broadcast Music, Inc. (BMI), 1964, 1967
    Subseries VIII: BMI contains documents related to the Standard Uniform Songwriters Contract and the Internal Revenue Service Notice of Levy. Items are arranged chronologically.
    - Standard Uniform Songwriters Contract, 1964
      - Contract between Bernettia Music Co. and Alan Freed and Buddy Wheel for "Big Daddy", 1964 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 13, Object 1-2)
      - Contract between Bernettia Music Co. and Alan Freed and Buddy Wheel for "The Day Before Tomorrow", 1964 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 13, Object 3-4)
      - Contract between Bernettia Music Co. and Alan Freed and Buddy Wheel for "My Fallen Idol", 1964 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 13, Object 5-6)
      - Contract between Bernettia Music Co. and Alan Freed and Buddy Wheel for "No One Must Know", 1964 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 13, Object 7-8)
      - Contract between Bernettia Music Co. and Alan Freed and Buddy Wheel for "(For Me) There Must Be You", 1964 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 13, Object 9)
      - Contract between Bernettia Music Co. and Alan Freed and Buddy Wheel for "My Arms Are Your Home", 1964 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 13, Object 10)
    - Internal Revenue Service Notice of Levy, 1967 June 28
      - For Period Ending 1957 December 31, 1967 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 14, Object 1)
      - For Period Ending 1958 December 31, 1967 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 14, Object 2)
      - For Period Ending 1959 December 31, 1967 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 14, Object 3)
  - Subseries 9: Cosnat Distributing Corporation, 1959 October, 1960 February
    Subseries IX: Cosnat Distributing Corporation materials are arranged chronologically.
    - #4558 - Alan Freed, 1959 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 15, Object 1-2)
    - District Attorney’s Office envelope: Alan Freed cancelled checks, 1960 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 15, Object 3-4)
  - Subseries 10: Fabian Theatres Corporation – Brooklyn Fox Theatre, 1959
    Subseries X: Fabian Theatre Corporation - Brooklyn Fox Theatre contains accounting records, including but not limited to daily box office statements, doorman's reports, hourly reports of ticket sales, and petty cash vouchers for Bonaire Music, as well as contracts and correspondence. Items are arranged chronologically. Some of the contracts are annotated.
    - Accounting, 1959 January 3-1959 April 7
      - Memo bill - pay to L. Levy, manager, 1959 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 16, Object 1)
      - Adding machine tape, 1959 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 16, Object 2)
      - Cashier's proof sheets, 1959 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 16, Object 3)
      - Daily box office statement, 1959 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 16, Object 4)